wow
so
[Music]
party
hello good evening good day everybody
welcome to episode 66 of the ask a
budget show
great to be back with you all
before we begin let me say hello to
everyone
2.0 deepak
ayush
and
everybody else good evening good day to
all of you great to have you all with me
tonight
and as you know today is a q a session
that's all about the live chat comments
so you can ask me questions in the live
chat and i will strive to answer your
questions i've also picked some more
questions from which were left over from
yesterday because i've got hundreds of
questions in the comments so i'll try to
answer some a few of the questions from
the comments as well
so
let us get going with a question with
the questions
this is from go ahead
and the question is tell me about big
foot creatures in the himalayas that's
an interesting question so uh it's not
called the bigfoot it's called the yeti
or the migoi
the that's the tibetan uh name i think
for this uh
for this it's called a cryptid i think
crypt
cryptid yes it's an unknown animal that
is said to exist high in the himalayas
in the frozen
regions
of the himalayas and uh
the local people in in
in tibet in bhutan even in sikkim they
speak about this this creature it's a
large man-sized
creature you would say it seems to be
very intelligent it's called the yeti or
the migoi
and there have been lots of sightings
reported sightings of this animal even
the indian army had taken
recently in in recent memory i believe
had released some pictures on on social
media on twitter i think of some
footprints of of an unknown creature
that looks like human-like footprints in
the snow you know tracks in the snow
that sort of thing and uh people have
been searching for this creature for
well over a century
and thus far we have no actual
hard evidence that this creature exists
but that so there's a lot of apocryphal
evidence lots of tales
there are some reported
there is some evidence of some skin of
the animal in some monasteries somewhere
and so on so forth and there is this
highway that goes through
that goes through sikkim i think india
where which which
apparently goes through the heartland of
the yeti so if you want to travel
through that place and try your luck at
exciting this legendary beast or
animal or creature then you can try that
so that's what i can tell you about it
it's never been actually discovered
maybe it does exist maybe it doesn't
exist we don't know for sure some people
say it's just the himalayan brown bear
which is an enormous big huge bear
uh 300 400 kilos huge bear so maybe
maybe it's that maybe some maybe some
people are playing that claiming that it
is just sightings of the himalayan brown
bear that looks like something else
and maybe there's an actual creature out
there which has never which may be so
intelligent that it has never been uh
discovered it wants to stay away from
humans maybe it knows how bad humans are
or whatever so
so we don't know for sure it's all
speculation as of today it's never been
actually discovered nobody has actually
taken
a genuine verifiable photograph of this
beast no video
and no dead bodies have been found no
skeletons so can't say for sure but it's
interesting that we have this beast
right here
in our own country
and in tibet
etc so
interesting
okay
let us
take some more questions
is it possible for a human to be
immortal is what rishikesh says well
as far as science goes it's not possible
for human to immortal uh humans seem to
have an
upper limit of lifespan that goes up a
little beyond 100 years
maybe 110 120 years i think the oldest
recorded
verifiable human being who lived to the
oldest age is about 140 144 maybe japan
maybe somewhere in southeast asia i'm
not sure where it was
so i think that's the uh established
record now people
especially in india claim that in the
old days people used to live for
hundreds of years and all that well okay
fine but uh we don't have any actual
verifiable evidence of that i'm not
saying it's not possible but from the
perspective of medical science there is
no evidence that any such thing is
possible
there is the process called aging which
we are all aware of
right it seems to be associated with the
shortening of the telomeres the ends of
the chromosomes in in human beings and
maybe in other animals as well
and that seems to be associated with
with aging so people are trying to
reverse that or try to try to slow that
down and maybe that is the key to
extending human lifespans
but
apart from that there is no real i mean
that's that's what they're trying
but it's not succeeded thus far
so from the perspective of science
medical science biology it doesn't seem
that it's possible for humans to be
immortal or even to extend their
lifespans beyond 100 into it well beyond
100 years right
and there's also the question of
consciousness because even if you are
able to extend the lifespan of the body
somehow
what happens to the brain i mean one of
the ways that we remember things the way
we create memories is to forget what's
been
stored in the memory in the past
so the brain
the mind seems to actively forget
certain things in order to create new
memories now if you let's say
hypothetically you're able to extend
your lifespan beyond 200 years will you
remember everything that happened 100
years ago
i am not sure if the human brain is
designed to have to retain memories that
go back that long you know that that
volume of memories and all that
so i don't know
if even even if you're able to extend
the lifespan of the physical body if the
mind will
survive that long will it be will it
survive or will the mind itself
deteriorate and become you know
uh it may become become pointless to to
for the body to survive that long if the
mind ceases to function in a coherent
and human-like way
so you know these are the questions
and uh so from the perspective of
medical science it's quite clear that
it's not possible for a human to be
immortal
so that's what i can answer from the
perspective of science and the data that
we have at hand
now this is a good question uh could you
discuss the scientific paper published
on nature that neeraj spoke about
regarding the ayurvedic prakriti in its
relation with genetics
good question so let me uh
let's go to google
and uh
hang in there let me let me try to find
the paper
one second once again
try to see if i have it stored somewhere
or
just give me a minute please
okay i have it booked bookmarked so i'll
be able to share it with you
so this is the paper cookies etc all
right
okay i think i was not able to share it
i think i'll be able to share it now
here we are here we are
so this is the paper that dr nirajara
spoke about the other day
uh it's called genome-wide analysis
correlates ayurveda prakriti so this is
an actual scientific paper it's not
whatever people would claim it is it was
published in 2015
and the abstract says that the practice
of ayurveda the traditional medicine of
india is based on the concept of three
major constitutional types
defined as prakriti to the best of our
knowledge no study has convincingly
correlated genomic variations with the
classification of prakriti
in the present study in this study which
i am showing right now uh we performed
genome-wide snp single nucleotide poly
polymorphism analysis
of 262 well classified male individuals
after screening more than 3000 subjects
belonging to the three prakritis we
found 52 snps that were significantly
different between prakritis without any
without any confounding effect of
stratification after 10 days to six
permutations
and so on so forth we further validated
our finding with 296 indian population
297 indian population samples with known
ancestry
uh and so on so we found that the pgm1
correlates with the phenotype of pitta
as prescribed in the ancient text of
character samhita
that the phenotypic classification of
india's traditional medicine has a
genetic basis and its prakriti based
medicine practice invoked for many
centuries
resonates with personalized medicine so
this essentially corroborates the
ayurvedic
classification of people into three
major constitutional types which is vata
pitta and kapha so there are three kinds
of people with three kinds of
constitutions what the type constitution
with the type constitution and the cover
type type constitution according to
ancient ayurvedic classification
and it seems now on the basis of this
paper which have just shown that this
classification actually has
bases in genetics so it actually means
that people have genetic differences
that fit into these three
classifications isn't that fascinating
so the science of genetics has actually
corroborated what ayurveda has been
saying for thousands of years that
people
can be classified into three separate
constitutional types vata picture kapha
so that's what dr niraj was speaking
about
i have
shown you the article let me show it to
you again in case you want to study this
you can google the title of the article
genome-wide analysis correlates ayurveda
prakruti it is by govindaraj thank raj
and you can read it up so it's a very
interesting study
and
you see our ancient uh sciences actually
are being corroborated with 21st century
scientific advancements isn't that
fascinating so great question great
question
right let us take
okay karthik says does the past present
and future co-exist so you're talking
about time so we don't really know for
sure
time is one of the great mysteries in
physics in science as is gravitation
and uh yeah so we don't quite know what
time is at the quantum level time it
doesn't even exist we're not sure
so that's how it is does the past
present future coexist
ah we there's no way to actually tell we
have we have a very fuzzy very fuzzy
understanding of what time is in our
differential equations which uh govern
newtonian physics and other kinds of
physics we have the uh
the variable as the time is one of the
variables dx by dt or dy by dt or
whatever you want to do it call it right
dm by dt
so time is one of the variables and
and uh so that's how systems in in
physics evolve
with time so time is an explicit
variable but we don't know what it is
where does time come from does it emerge
from somewhere does it emerge from the
quantum level of reality
uh
is it does time exist everywhere
if you had a different i mean is it
possible to construct a hypothetical
universe that doesn't have time
is time related to thermodynamics the
evolution of states
is time quantum in nature do you have uh
atoms and molecules of time
uh where does time emerge from is it an
intrinsic property of the universe or is
it an emergent property of the universe
we don't know any of these things
according to a new paper that has been
published recently it looks like i mean
it's
uh this new paper says i'm not sure who
i don't remember who the uh
physicist was who the author of the
paper but um
it's because of d coherence or quantum
decoherence that that creates the the
perception of time so it may be an
emergent effect
uh quantum entanglement and decoherence
and all that so
so it's there's no no way to prove it as
of today but it's an interesting
perspective
uh so we don't know for sure uh from a
philosophical perspective there are all
kinds of i mean india indian philosophy
has a very clear idea i mean has a very
clear view
of what time is
and all that but from a scientific
perspective we don't know for sure in
philosophy and science don't mix these
are two separate
domains
of
of investigation
so science is separate from philosophy
philosophy and the science is also
separate
from
essentially actually science is a subset
of philosophy but philosophy uh it deals
with with uh
matters that
go beyond science so so science is
purely is is definitely within
philosophy but philosophy deals with
certain matters that do not uh
fall in the realm of science because it
can you can discuss things that are
non-physical
and non-observable in philosophy in
science you can't so you know so that's
how it is so that's
what i can say in brief about time past
present future we don't know for sure
uh these things we have a perception of
time we have a perception
of the past
we essentially live in the past right
all our memories deal with the past
all our understanding of the world the
universe
is
is based on our past experiences and
what we have studied about the past so
our understanding of the world uh has
the basis as a basis in in what we have
experienced in the past
and
so from our perspective
the past
seems to exist we have uh we have our
stored memories
that are all about things that events
that happened in the past
i think animals also have some sort of
perception of time they also see they
also clearly have memories they also
have behavioral patterns that are that
are based on the experiences they have
had in the past
time seems to flow differently from
people from person to person time seems
to flow uh time seems to elapse faster
as you grow older that's what
that's so that's the human experience
is it the same for a dog or a cat or a
sparrow we don't know
so
so that's the big mystery what is time
is it something we perceive and is it an
illusion is it an emergent phenomenon is
it an intrinsic phenomenon past present
future do they actually exist or are
these just concepts we our our mind is
created in order to make sense of the
world we don't know for sure and that's
the one of the big mysteries
so very interesting question but
nobody has an answer as of today
all right let's see some more
questions
current says is mathematics and
astronomy related yes of course
mathematics is the basis of all physics
astronomy is a subset of physics
mathematics describes the uh mathematics
deals with these regularities and
patterns that underlie the physical
universe
and therefore uh if you want to study
astronomy you do need an understanding a
good understanding of mathematics
especially
differential equations and things like
that maybe general relativity and you
need an understanding of newtonian
physics
more or less in astronomy astrophysics
is totally different but yes so all
science especially all the physical
sciences
uh are
you you can study them and do research
in them only if you have a very good
understanding of the mathematical tools
that are required to uh investigate
those phenomena
so yes there is a clear relationship
nishant says why didn't the indus river
dry up at the time the saraswati was
drying up well it's because these two
rivers originated in a very different
the origin of these surivas was very
different the indus the sindhu river
originates deep in the himalayas it it
originates from glacial melt water from
the water that melts from the melting of
snows from of snow and glaciers in the
himalayas so that is where the sindhu
that is how the sindhu uh
originates in himalayas now the
saraswati also was a river that
originated in the himalayas but the vast
majority of its water
came from
not glacial melt water but from the
indian monsoon and about 8 000 years ago
the indian monsoon was much much heavier
than what it is today
and around 6000 bce
approximately
the indian monsoon began to
monotonically decline slowly gradually
the intensity and the volume of rain
that would be unleashed upon the indian
subcontinent every year slowly started
declining that's called climate change
climate change is a natural phenomenon
it also has a human component today so
because of climate change over of
several millennia
from 6080 to around uh 6000 bc sorry to
around 2000 bc the monsoon declined
monotonically
and by around 2000 bce or something the
the monsoon had uh
declined to such an extent that this
river the saraswati which was mostly fed
by monsoon rains it
stopped
it it shrunk up
it dried to a significant extent and
it's it stopped reaching the sea
it i think it uh it appears that it uh
dried out
somewhere in the region of the thar
desert the third as it may
most likely was a lake in the past
caused by this slow decline of the
saraswati
and today also the riverbed is there if
you go northwards towards haryana etc
you find that this month this river
still has water it is a monsoon fed
river even today and that's why it's a
seasonal river
so the uh saraswati was fed by monsoon
rains it was a massive
gigantic river if you look at the
brahmaputra today it originates in the
himalayas just like the saraswati did
but more than 80 85 of its water
of the brahmaputra
it comes from the the
comes from the rain forest in the in the
region of arunachal pradesh from
rainfall and all that
so even if the chinese block the river
the dam it up it's not going to cause
much of an effect in india because more
than 85 of the water comes from
arunachal pradesh from rainfall and all
and such other related processes from
the rainforest
so the saraswati was similar and because
the monsoon declined significantly over
several thousand years that is the
reason why it dried out but the other
rivers
in the sundu region
present-day punjab
did not dry out because they were main
their major source of water was the
himalayan glacial melt water so that's
why only one river dried out but the
sindhu did not dry out neither did the
other rivers in this region
okay
lots of questions
um
let's find something that has not been
answered before
very
interesting
see i i am
i am not very inclined to talk about
rajputs and chatrias and this cast and
that cast i'm tired of that because they
it just causes so much fractiousness so
much fiction but this gentleman akshat
gerg
has asked a very
very interesting question
you spoke about the bravery of rajputs
but they gave in to akbar and later to
the british
they lived in palaces while the indian
while the andeans were dying of famines
how were they brave what does endian
mean
is is akshat a real name or are you from
pakistan or are you but who knows
something else
because this is this is a something that
pakistanis used to to write about india
and there are india
so this gentleman seems to be a
pakistani who is masquerading under an
indian hindu name
interesting anyhow the question is you
spoke about the bravery of rajputs how
do you what is the definition of bravery
the definition of bravery is that you uh
face danger you are afraid but you still
face it and you know the risk you know
the risk you may die and yet you go
ahead and do whatever is required of you
that's called bravery
now
the rajputs gave in to akbar apparently
so this is how it happened you see
dutch boots were brave
nobody can deny that
but
some of the rajput leaders did mistakes
rajputs believed they had this code of
chivalry that you don't uh
they don't
attack someone who who is who has turned
their back and who is who has apologized
or who has asked for forgiveness and all
that thing which is
clearly not practical
it is it it is something that that works
only in satyagru
doesn't work in kalyuk but
that's how it was and that's why they
lost so so you had uh
uh the great queen nayaki devi who
defeated that guy gori
but she let him get away the battle
happened in gujarat
in northern gujarat and he was allowed
to escape all the way to afghanistan so
she was a brave lady the her warriors
were brave but she allowed the enemy to
go away to escape she could have had her
soldiers pursue him and when he was
trying to escape and kill him i mean
afghanistan is a thousand more than
thousand kilometers away from gujarat
surely you can pursue him and catch up
with him and
eliminate him right the great terrorist
gory similarly the great the great king
prithviraj johan very brave man very
noble man no doubt
but he again
spared
this guy guri
right
the he was defeated in um
in present-day haryana he was allowed to
escape all the way to lahore which he
was under under his
control at the time gori
so again he this guy could have been
pursued he had lost the battle he was
he was seriously wounded but he was
allowed to get away
so it is because of these things that
eventually guri was able to prevail
and and defeat prithvira chohan and
these are the reasons why
later on
rajput kings had to make compromises
with the turks
so you know what the great vishnu gupta
said he said that the highest morality
for a king is that his people and his
kingdom should prosper
that's what he said
so if you are a small king of a small
principality in rajputana or in india
and you have this great turk
who has conquered significant parts of
northern india was a very over
overwhelmingly large powerful army like
akbar
right
and this guy says that i'm gonna wipe
you out unless you become my vasal
so what will this small
rajput king do
he will have to make a compromise or the
alternative is that all his people die
that's why they had to make compromises
that's why they have to get they had
they were forced to offer their
daughters as wives to this to the turks
it's because of the
mistakes that people like maharani nikki
devi did and maharaja johan did
now many people have accused me of of of
hating prathira johan i don't hate him
for god's sake i don't hate the guy
i'm just disappointed that
he made these mistakes
i know he was a great king who am i to
talk about him come on
that's that's the thing about history if
you don't understand history if you
don't scrutinize the past and if you
don't draw the correct lessons from the
past then you're going to repeat the
mistakes right so these are the reasons
why
uh this gentleman
i mean the why the rajputs apparently
gave in to the to the mughals to to
people like akbar akbar
and yes they had to compromise so that
that people could stay could stay alive
and
live in reasonable dignity right
some rajputs did not
compromise we know who they are
ranasanga and who else is it
they fought but what happened they were
exiled they had to live in forest their
descendants still wander around india
right so that's what happened the
compromise they did not compromise but
they paid a horrible price for that
and
living in palaces i mean
this is the thing people
i mean
do you know the difference between a
fortress and a palace
i think i've explained this in the past
i even may have a couple of short clips
about that please revisit that mr akshat
garg
indians
see there were no famines during the end
during the
the the uh major famines were engineered
by the british there were a few famines
during the turkic occupation of india
northern india but the major famines
happened during the british times at
which time india was broken
india had been broken india had been
subjugated
and
so that's how it went how were they
brave
okay i'm not going to take this anymore
so i i hope that throws some light upon
the process by which india was
subjugated it's a slow gradual process
a few
great kings make some mistakes and
later down
centuries down the line people have to
keep paying the price
for the mistakes they made
so we have to
clearly understand what happened and
whether you think the rajputs were great
or not whether you have a great deal of
respect for the nobility
and the courage and the character and
personality of mr prithira johan
but you have to acknowledge the fact
that he made a grave terrible mistake
that india
is still paying the price for
so that's just how it is if you disagree
well you are free to disagree but
that's that's the way i see it and
that's the way you would see it
logically
all right
says the slavs the europeans and
iranians try to appropriate their
culture as vedic and call themselves
aryans
what's your take on this
so first of all
there is no such thing as an aryan race
if there is any any
ethnic group that should be called the
aryans logically
it's the indians and the iranians
the iranians the ancient iranians like
i've said many many times where
migrants from india
they were the parshwa clan of the
rigvedic people the parshwa people
and they gave because of their name the
name of the clan
the partial clan that's why the name of
the country became persia
their capital was parshvapor which the
greeks called persepolis
and they used the term arya as an ethnic
self-designator
so in india arya was an adjective it
means noble refined civilized and so on
in iran arya became
the ethnic adjective
or the ethnic noun you know ethnic self
designator
so they used uh the persians the the
persians during the manish dynasty
achaemenid dynasty etc they called
themselves arya as in an ethnic term
and that's how this entire thing
happened so i don't see anything wrong
if the iranians want to call themselves
arya or aryans
they're they don't the iranians are now
all shia muslims so i don't see them
trying to appropriate indian culture or
vedic culture for themselves their
culture was a post vedic culture it was
significantly close to indian culture
even today the zero students who escaped
from uh from persia who live in india if
you see the rituals and traditions there
you can see the similarities between
their traditions and the vedic
traditions so so i don't see anything
wrong with them
trying to say that we are the
descendants of the vedic people and
their culture is an offshoot of the
vedic culture so that's perfectly fine
the slavic people europeans etc
well they are the descendants of the
omnia invaders who
were indian in origin they were clearly
people who had abandoned the vedic
customs and culture they indulged in a
horrible rampage across europe they
massacred all the european males
wherever they conquered and they
well they had children with the european
females and that's how the modern
european population was born
so clearly they did not follow vedic
customs and traditions and morality
because
you know massacre genocide is obviously
something that
vedic
culture would
never
consider to be righteous or good
in any way
so
the europeans the slavs etc if you look
at their pre-christian culture and
religion and all that it is clearly a
continuation a broken mangled
uh continuation of the vedic customs the
entirety of eurasia from india from the
indian subcontinent all the way to
western europe to ireland etc was one
single cultural continuum it was one
single culture with lots of very
interesting different local
manifestations
so the nordic gods thor etc these are
essentially the same thing as the vedic
pantheon the greek pantheon zeus
and the others are a continuation of the
vedic pantheon of gods indra and all
that same as saying for the roman
pantheon same for the slavic pantheon so
their culture is an offshoot of the
ancient
prime primordial
vedic culture
but their culture is clearly not vedic
it is a post-vedic culture
uh i'm not sure if they are trying to
appropriate vedic vedic culture i don't
think that i mean that would be actually
laughed off
and yeah the iron invasion theory is an
appropriate is an attempt to claim that
all of this indian culture came from
europe which is
well it's on its last legs now so that's
my take on it it's not to be taken very
seriously what the the thing that needs
to be taken seriously is the attempt to
steal yoga pranayama etc this individual
called
hof is now
peddling his so-called wim hof method
which is nothing but pranayama pranayama
he calls it the wim hof method of
breathing in and out that is bastrika or
pranayam and the the cold water and cold
air treatment which he is talking about
is something he has these ideas he has
got from from the sadhus who live in the
himalayas so this is nothing but
outright cultural theft and it's been
marketed it's become millionaire i
believe
selling all this
the wim hof method of cultural cultural
theft
so these are the things that we need to
take more seriously the theft of yoga
the theft of
uh
pranayama and all that this is something
that needs concerted action
from the indian government
so that's what i have spoken about in
the past as well so
so that's what i can say about this
her says have you read the indian
renaissance book by sanjeev sunderl my
thoughts on it
no
unfortunately i haven't read it sorry i
haven't
okay let's take some more questions
dan stacks says whatever people say
after all romans have influenced the
whole world both culturally and
militarily scientifically
funny to see you people are still
colonized mentally so cool all right
nice observation sir thank you for your
two cents
all right what else
uh aka the guy says did homony and the
thales have more brain power than
sapiens if if yes
why couldn't they survive cognitive
revolution and
could the sapiens and neanderthals mate
together
so uh
we have a good understanding of what our
neanderthal cousins were like
uh
i think they were
if you look at the the size of their
brains etc if you because we have
evidence from neanderthal skulls and all
that it looks like the brain volume was
at least the same if not more than that
of homo sapiens
so uh
if if cranial capacity of brain capacity
the volume of the vein is an indicator
they were at least as intelligent if not
more intelligent than homo sapiens so
uh so the question is why couldn't this
survive i'm not sure what the cognitive
revolution is but why couldn't they
survive that's the question maybe homo
sapiens brought with them
certain illnesses certain diseases that
these guys
neanderthals may not have been resistant
to maybe that is a possibility
could sapiens and neanderthals mate
together yes
uh
it has been
discovered that the majority of the
non-european
uh sorry non-african human population
con has
some neanderthal dna between two to four
or even six percent of
non-african uh people have uh
sorry all
the majority of non-african people have
between two and six percent
neanderthal but uh recently i came to
know that indians don't have neanderthal
or most indians don't have it which is a
very interesting observation
so to answer your question that's a
digression to answer your question yes
uh homo sapiens and hormone in the
neanderthals were
very
uh were both subspecies of of human
beings and they could certainly mate
together and that's why many many many
people who are non-african
have a certain amount of neanderthal dna
so that's what i can say we still don't
know for sure why the neanderthals were
wiped out earlier it was said that they
were stupid they were slow and the homo
sapiens were more agile and more
intelligent and they
competed with them and and
killed them out
but
there is a very simplistic
view of things clearly that was not the
case
there may have been coexistence
cooperation instead of competition
and
maybe there were some other factors that
caused the slow gradual decline and
eventual end
of hormone endothelius so that is
something that still
needs to be investigated but yeah
clearly
it's possible that it was uh
certain pathogens or certain diseases
that
our sapiens ancestors may have brought
with them that could have hastened or
caused the decline of
neanderthals
okay this is a question i get hundreds
of times
ramayana mentions four tasked elephants
in sundar khan
doesn't mean it happened four million
millions of years ago so listen we
know we have a very good understanding
of the
timeline of human evolution yes
a million years ago there was no homo
sapiens
i mean there was no there were no
anatomically modern human beings
the oldest evidence of anatomically
modern
homo sapiens
is from about 250 000 years before today
in north africa
so that's how old homo sapiens is and
that too is an archaic version of homo
sapiens
even the homo sapiens who lived a
hundred thousand years ago one lakh
years ago
where in some ways different from what
we are today they would have looked
different
and uh
yeah there were differences but they
were anatomically
quite similar to us
so if you go back a million years
there was no homo sapiens
and ramayana is about homo sapiens it's
about indian culture right
if there was no homo sapiens a million
years ago then how would you have
haramayan or or or
indian culture indian civilization
about two to four million years ago we
had the divergence between humans and
chimpanzees
so about four million years ago
the ancestors of humans were the same as
the ancestors of chimpanzees
so please understand the chronology of
human evolution and
and it simply doesn't
doesn't fit
the millions of years old timeline of
that some people believe in of indian
history it simply doesn't work that way
uh the best scientific data and
understanding that we have says that
human beings
homo sapiens is not older than 250 000
years
uh old
so that simply doesn't fit this this
world view right so
that's what i can say about it
okay now about four tusked elephants
it appears that uh
there were some species of elephants
that had four tusks that they existed a
few million years ago so that's that's
perplexing of course
that's perplexing
but the thing is we cannot we should not
try and take everything that is
mentioned
in the ramayana mahabharata as
something that is literally correct
there is much that has been embellished
there are a lot of embellishments
much of it is allegorical
you cannot take everything at face value
it is called etihas which means that the
major events that are mentioned
in the account are historical events
but the way they have been described may
not be always 100 percent accurate and
factual
there may be certain embellishments that
are added on top of the actual
facts
so that's what i can say so i don't have
an answer as as per the as far as the
four task element goes because in recent
human history there has been no foretest
elephant i think the four
tasked elephants died out
uh a few million years ago most likely i
don't have the exact information but
something like that
so we haven't really coexisted with
those
four tusks elephants which which is
perplexing so maybe
it is not to be taken literally or maybe
there have been may have been
a species of elephant that was like this
that we are still not aware of that is
also a possibility but that seems to be
less likely to me
so that's what i can say about this
okay let's take some more questions
okay this is by anish kulkarni
says movies music cartoons play an
essential role in building a nation's
soft power for example k-pop anime
japanese enemies etc
is india's entertainment sector doing
enough to grow india's soft power and to
build a narrative let me add something
to this if you watch uh all the
streaming services today amazon prime
netflix and there may be many more
uh hbo
let's let's talk about the ones that are
popular in india i think amazon prime
and netflix are the most popular in
india look at the kind of shows they
have there
so many korean shows aren't there
there is this show called kingdom there
are many detective shows and all there
is this squid game
all of these things
they build up a nation's image
and it's yeah it is certainly something
that builds up a nation's image and
prestige and
it builds up what is known as soft power
if you look at k-pop it's immensely
popular i think globally even in india
among teenagers generation
z
the millennials cetera kpox k-pop seems
to be very popular
right even though people may not
understand the lyrics because they i
think they must be in korean and still
it's so popular look at japanese anime
japanese enemy is popular the world over
so this is what plays like you say an
essential critical role in building a
nation's image
and soft power is india's entertainment
sector doing enough to grow india soft
power and build a narrative india's
entertainment sector is doing less than
zero
look at the quality of indian shows on
streaming services it's garbage
i mean i have
i have not found anything that it is to
my lake liking
i mean um
the quality is terrible
and the themes they explore are so
regressive
it's all about portraying india in a
negative light so that's why i'm saying
they're doing less than zero they're
actually portraying india in a negative
manner
if you show the if you see there may be
a few indian shows on netflix and amazon
prime what's the quality what are the
themes
so india's entertainment sector and
let's talk about bollywood
how are they portraying india
does bollywood represent indian culture
does the music that come out of comes
out of bollywood represent indian
culture is bollywood dance
representative of indian culture no no
no
and today i get the feeling when i look
at indians
it looks like they always have some
bollywood song going on in their head
and they're all dancing to it in their
imagination
that's the deep brainwashing that we are
seeing
of of especially young indians by
bollywood the kind of dances that come
out of bollywood are of
i have no words to express that and the
kind of music that comes out of
bollywood it is not indian music
it doesn't represent indian culture it
represents represents something else
so the indian entertainment sector is
doing less than zero to grow india soft
power it is growing other nations and
other cultures soft power
it is portraying other cultures
as being part of indian culture and so
on and so forth so you know
that's
that is very disappointing and i think
it is time for uh
for entertainment in india to go beyond
bollywood
today i think anybody with a small
budget
can produce a world-class
entertainment show
a world-class
documentary i think people in small
towns also
today
they have the equipment that is
necessary that is required to do a
world-class job at uh
at creating
tv series and all that so i i don't know
why it's not happening maybe india is
still not uh
financially prosperous enough maybe
another five ten years but uh to answer
to come back and summarize and answer
your question no india's entertainment
sector is not doing
anything
to grow india's soft power and to build
any kind of narrative about india if any
narrative is being built it's about
showing india in a bad light
denigrating india's indigenous culture
and promoting a foreign culture as
indian culture that's what they are
doing
okay let's take some more questions
um let's see let's see let's see my
views about somebody i don't have any
views about anyone i have views about
historical figures and people who matter
globally i don't have views about
any other
people
i i don't think we should be discussing
uh
individuals too much we should discuss
history we should discuss science
geopolitical people
at a global level who matter at a global
scale that's what i would like to
comment about other people i will not
comment about
okay this is by so so um
does the sumerian civilization link with
india do they have indian genes do they
have indian influence in their culture
i think the sumerian culture was quite
different from india but they may have
clearly had some influences
they did worship certain goddesses that
do seem to have
have
some traits that are present in indian
goddesses like durga lakshmi etc
they uh
what was the sumerian goddess was it the
babylonian goddess sumerian goddess
inanna
and so on so yeah they had some
goddesses and some some
deities some divinities that do seem to
have some
some connection with india and i am sure
that there were trade and other
connections
between
this region and ancient india we know
that there was once a war
between um
the accordion empire
under
king rimush
and the marahashi kingdom which was
allied with
the indus valley region the saraswati
hindu
civilization
so it appears that some soldiers indian
soldiers went and fought on behalf
of the marhashi kingdom against king
rimosh and according to the korean
sources they were able to prevail and so
on so forth
so there were clearly uh connections
between
the middle east of that time
and india
and we have we are able to find india's
the uh
saraswati hindu seals
in the middle east as well
even in parts of arabia like oman and so
on so yes there were definitely
connections i don't know about indian
genes if you look at the people of
middle of the middle east today even
central asia you will see distinctive
indian appearances in some people that
may of course be due to
the fact that the turks took away
millions of indian women and children
mostly as slaves
in the in the
in the islamic world and that's why many
people in that region in the islamic
world today would have indian ancestry
of some kind especially matrilineal
ancestry so maybe that's why they many
arabs and many people from this region
may look like indians
but uh so that's why if you if you were
to
uh do a genetic uh study of the
modern
middle eastern population you would
certainly find indian matrilineal
lineages but that may date back to more
recent events
but uh
so uh
to summarize i would say that so this
civilization did have trade
uh links with india
maybe some cultural links but we don't
know
to what extent that was because as we
our historians have not studied that
so i don't have the
sufficient data to answer this in detail
but yes
from whatever data we know there clearly
looks like there were some cultural
links and there were definitely trade
links for sure
right
swastika says how does gravity affect
time
so there's this phenomenon called time
dilation and special relativity if you
study general relativity special
relativity you will see that the
presence of mass
affects space time it causes the
curvature of space time
this curvature of space time is uh
felt is what we feel as the force of
gravity it also affects time so if you
move closer to a massive object
you find the time that time actually
slows down and we are able to measure
this because the time that the time that
we the speed at which time flows on the
surface of the planet is different from
the
speed at which time flows
uh in orbit around the earth and we are
able to measure the differences
so that's what happens so gravity does
affect time time slows down near the in
the presence of a massive object and
there is a clear relationship which
which we have the equations of special
relativity that uh
through which you can calculate the
exact effect of gravity on time and uh
to to give you a very popular example
watch that movie what's it called uh
interstellar
in which this effect uh
plays a big role
in the story
so yes gravity does affect time
okay um
dinesh methi says what's the current
status of archaeology in dwarka i think
there's nothing being done right now
unfortunately it seems that there is no
archaeology being done in dwarka which
is disappointing because it's a very
interesting archaeological site
one of the major archaeological sites so
let's take a look at the map and let's
see what this
place looks like
so this is uh
wherever we in arabia okay this is india
dwarka is over here at this
this is where it is
this is the
modern city of dwarka
and
if you look here why is everything in
arabic very interesting
so this is the city of dwarka the modern
day city of dwarka and off the coast of
this dwarka our baby is another dwarka
there is an older dwarka somewhere else
so i think it could be most likely here
i think there are two
sites of dwarka
but but let's say it's this one so maybe
a few
few uh tens or or dozens of meters off
the coast
you have an entire underwater sunken
city that has been discovered there it
was discovered in the 1980s and
after that it looks like the entire
thing has been hushed up and there has
been no
further research
and then there is this island over here
which is called beit dwarka
i believe they have also found uh
archaeological
what on earth okay
evidence of archaeological ancient
archaeological sites on this island as
well
if you look here at the satellite images
you can see certain uh
certain what what clearly looks like
man-made walls
over here which seem to be very ancient
so you can see this is a very ancient uh
island and it seems to have uh
evidence of ancient human
uh settlements and activity over here
but unfortunately i don't think there's
anything going on right now any
archaeological work being done over here
because we know
that dwarka was the
was where lord krishna ruled from for
several years
so it was
it was where he was king right dwarka so
was it here or was it in the sunken city
over here
or was it in this
island of beit dwarka we not don't know
for sure and that's what we need to find
out
i think there was this uh
there is this
show this is this american tv show
called expedition
unknown or something josh gates i
believe
uh i think they had an episode on dwarka
in which they came to this island and
they discovered a very ancient wall over
here
maybe this is the one which we're seeing
and they also did some underwater work
but i'm not sure if they were able to
find anything so it's clearly something
that we need to investigate
in much greater detail we need to spend
we need to invest money and time in this
this is the asis duty to do all that but
nothing is being done right now
they are busy renovating turkic
monuments and british monuments
but no nothing here
so unfortunate
okay let's take some more questions
yeah no i don't know about this tell me
the history about the lingayats and how
they distinct from v rashevas
and hindus look what i know is that
lingayats are just hindus today they
have been given the status of a minority
in a non-hindi non-hindu community etc
this is all political
nonsense they're just trying to divide
hindus further and further
apart from that i i haven't studied
the history of the lingayats and the
veerashevas and all that so
so unfortunately i can't answer i i am
not aware of this i don't have this you
know sufficient knowledge to give a
to give an answer right
but they are not distinct in any way
from indians from hindus
it's just the same
i mean if you go to any any any place in
india you will find
a very uh
distinctive local form
of hinduism very distinctive traditions
and and
rituals and all that
it doesn't mean it's a it's different
from hinduism but that's how they are
interpreting things now
for the sake of getting votes so it's
very unfortunate but they are in no way
different from hindus
okay
okay let's take some more questions
climate change so so man asks
counting in terms of years
how many years do you think it will take
us humans to revert the amount to
reverse
the amount of damage we have brought up
on the planet and what should be our
first and most important step
i don't think it's going to be humanly
possible to reverse
the uh
the uh damage
we have done on the planet i don't think
we can reverse it
uh climate change has always been a
natural process it's always been a
reality on the planet and what's
happened since the industrial revolution
the last two three hundred years
is that the west has disgorged an
enormous amount of carbon
into the atmosphere carbon and other
particulate matter and all that through
mainly through burning coal and fossil
fuels the west
the western world
from the second half of the 20th century
onwards the east
has been trying to catch up and
industrialize and now they are trying to
stop that they're trying to slow us down
they're trying to now blame india and
china for the pollution
and for all the climate change which
they have caused
now i am not saying that we should
not do anything
what i'll what i think what i can tell
you is that it's
it's practically impossible to reverse
the damage we've caused all the carbon
that has been disgorged into the
atmosphere
it's there it's not uh going to
be reversed anytime soon what we can do
the first now now what you're asking is
the first and most important step i
think one of the most important steps is
to
try and ban plastic all the disposable
plastic bags and all that which are
choking the oceans
now what we are finding is that these
plastic these plastics have been in the
ocean for several decades they have been
broken down the plastic still exists as
plastic but it's broken down into micro
particles so you have these micro
plastic granules and particles that
there are everywhere now in the oceans
in the rivers in the drinking water
we're using plastic bottles for water i
think there is a long term effect even
this has
on on the composition of the water some
of these plastic materials may be
leaching into the water and if you look
at tap water or drinking water you now
find that there is there are
micro micro plastics
particles everywhere
everywhere
i think you even find that in in when
they slaughter animals for meat you find
micro plastics in fish
in the meat of animals
in in even in milk i believe
so i think it is
extremely important to stop dumping
plastic into the oceans the damage that
has already been done maybe we can find
some ways of slowly uh trying to undo it
but the oceans are full of plastic it's
it's destroying
the oceanic environment it's killing
oceanic
marine wildlife
fish
plankton larger mammals
and so on
and it's going to eventually end up
poisoning
the land animals and humans
so i think one of the most important
things we can start with
is to ban disposable plastics
and maybe try and move away from plastic
i know plastic is now an essential part
of human activity human life i i'm sure
i have plastics all over me i'm sure
there's plastic here as well
this button is plastic you see plastics
are everywhere but we need to find a way
to stop using plastic that much
so that is one of the most important
things we can do
and try to move to renewable energy
uh
solar energy wind energy
uh and all that maybe nuclear energy if
you can do it safely i'm sure we can do
it safely it's one of the safest forms
of energy so and and move away from
fossil fuels you know slowly so these
things
need to be done and
so climate change is a very real thing
the environment is definitely under a
significant amount of threat we are
seeing extinctions of various species
happening we seem to be in the middle of
a mass extinction event that we have
triggered off humans have triggered off
so yeah this is a time of crisis but
it's a crisis that's unfolding very
slowly so we don't realize it but once a
few decades pass you will see the change
temperatures will rise
2 to 3 degrees in the next 100 years
which is very significant
so yeah
the himalayas may soon be devoid of snow
and ice antarctica may
no longer have glaciers
water levels may rise coastal cities
chennai mumbai and so on you know may
may disappear the entire nation of the
maldives may disappear the bangladeshis
may be into a deep crisis dhaka
everything will go under the water where
will they go
and someone was asking me what should
india do about this
and so on yeah you know so so it's a big
crisis and these are the things that
need to be done
urgently my friends urgently
but we
we citizens
can't do anything about it it's it's for
the world leaders to do this
so they need to find some sort of uh
way of reaching at a consensus and
you know what what they call it in
politics a common minimum plan or
something like that so something needs
to be done
or let me take some questions from the
comments a couple of questions uh
here's an interesting question by
knowledge seeker
i'm asking the same question again and
again
can you tell when will our bharat get a
great leader by seeing the patterns of
world history
very interesting question
history is full of patterns that repeat
themselves
and seeing the patterns of world history
i would say that india is currently
most likely at the cusp of a significant
major change what's happening see what's
happened since 1947 is that the people
of india have been deliberately kept
very poor the economy has been kept very
low deliberately
through design and indian side we have
been kept illiterate and indians have
not been taught their truest dream today
i get the feeling i get the sense that
slowly the nation is awakening
somebody asked me why did people keep on
voting nero again and again as a prime
minister because they did not know who
he was they did not understand history
they did not understand anything they
were kept illiterate and when you're
illiterate you just believe what the
leaders tell you
today what you are seeing
is that people are waking up people are
now beginning to question
the
mainstream wisdom the mainstream
narrative of everything
so i think that india is on the verge of
a significant change and the significant
uh change in the mindset
of people especially among the teenagers
of today and the youngsters of today
people who are below the age of 25
and i know from the statistics and data
that more than 50 of the viewers of my
channel are below 25 years of age
so i think
that india will not get one great leader
india will get several great leaders
and i think that
these great leaders will come from the
people who are watching this channel
i i can i am certain
that within the next 20 years
the viewer the people who are watching
this video right now and the ones who
will watch this video in the future
they are going to throw
this this audience is going to produce
great leaders not one but multiple great
leaders in various spheres of
human endeavor maybe
in in business in industry in
entrepreneurship in technology in in
education in politics
not just leaders of india but global
leaders worldwide leaders
i i make the prediction right now that
you yes you could be one of those
leaders i think in the next 20 years
many people who are watching this
channel right now are going to be among
the leaders great leaders of india in
the world
so uh
this change is upon us
and the leaders of tomorrow have already
been born they are learning right now
they are understanding the world and
they need to take the world seriously
and get to work and within the next 20
years we will see significant
changes
in india in leadership i am very
positive about this so it's a very good
question and that's what i think about
it
okay back to the live questions
why do you want to present why not
president under a new constitution think
bigger sir think bigger
okay let's take some other questions
mahakal says i have read a lot of
western feminist theory they don't give
a complete solution indian culture is
given the biggest feminist
that is makali
can you speak about her ideology well
let me talk to you about feminism
feminism is something that emerged from
the west see historically traditionally
the west has been extremely misogynistic
women have been less than second-class
citizens of the west
they were treated brutally they were
oppressed they were given no rights no
freedoms they had no future except being
a housewife and being a baby producing
machine that's how women lived in the
west now what happened is that in the us
in the 19th and 19th century there was a
shift in attitudes and women women began
to begin to
demand
changes
and that's where feminism comes from
and it is
certainly
something that started with extremely
good intentions of liberating women from
the shackles
or that the western culture had placed
them under the patriarchal shackles of
western culture so this was a rebellion
against this it was a gradual rebellion
because you know they were treated quite
brutally the
men had the right to beat women and they
essentially owned the women they married
you know that's how it was
so that's that's the
milieu that's the environment that
feminism emerged out of it was a cry for
help it was
an attempt to to make things better for
women
and it had a very good intentions
and slowly women were able to win more
rights you know
female suffrage the right to vote
the right to be equal citizens and so on
and so forth the right to stand for
office the right to get an education
and all these things
but afterwards later what happened is
that they tried to force fit that onto
every culture in the world
because we are so misogynistic it means
everybody has to be misogynistic and
because we are the west we have whiter
skin that means the people in the east
must be even worse than us
especially the polytheists
hindus and that's why they have tried
they're now trying to portray indian
society hindu society as being
misogynistic there is that regressive
patriarchal backward on all those things
that's been
a project that's been underway for at
least 200 300 years right
so uh
feminism
came out of a certain socio-cultural
context that is the misogynistic the
misogyny and oppression of women
in western society
so it was a solution to that problem in
that context
it has no relevance
in indian society
indian culture indian civilization has
always
has always respected women
and always treated women as more than
equals
so there is no need for any feminism in
india
in certain strata of indian indian
society i expect feminism would have
some relevance but not in indian hindu
society not an indian culture and
civilization
so like like you mentioned we have so
many great strong women in in
in the
hindu pantheon and in indian history as
well
right many great brave women who have
taken up arms who have taken up
leadership positions who have changed
society
we can give so many examples
ronnie lakshmi by uh the great hulyaba
hulkar uh
we recently spoke about uh
what's her name the great queen nayaki
devi solanki even though she let gory go
she spared him but she defeated him she
her son who was the king was just an
infant so she
went
to war she she actually participated in
the battle she may not have actually
gone and fought but she was there and
that shows there is skin in the game if
they had lost she would have lost her
life but she went there and that's
that's how brave indian women were
luxury by the great lady she lost her
life for the british the killer
through treachery and all that and we
have so many examples of great indian
women who have been intellectual
scholars many of the verses
the mantras of the rig veda were
composed by female
intellectuals
female scholars right female rishikas
gargi lopamudra and so many more right
so we don't need this western feminism
they should learn from us actually
but that will happen only when we wake
up my friends when we wake up and we
stop seeing ourselves as inferior
and backward and misogynistic and
everything is wrong with indian society
and all the solutions will come from the
west no
the solutions will come from india
we are the superior culture
we have been the superior culture of
late we know what's happened
india has been under foreign occupation
for a thousand years and that's where
everything went wrong and that's where
certain
unfortunate things have crept into
indian society once we are liberated
from the foreign influences and foreign
occupation which we still are not once
that happens
the self-writing of indian society will
happen naturally that's just how society
evolves
so what happens is we need freedom india
is still not free
1947 was just a transfer of power it was
dominion status 1950 was a colonial
colonized republic and we are still
colonized
so when when india really gains its
independence then things will go in the
right direction
diogo says didn't india get infected by
misogynism in any way yes we were
infected by
by foreign cultures
which treated women like
you know how they regard women
they regard their own women and any
women in the world as merely pieces of
meat
so yes india was infected and still is
infected with that
uh
within in certain sectors of society in
certain minds with that uh
mindset with the perspective
so yes that's what i said in the past
1000 years india has been under foreign
occupation by barbarians by people with
inferior cultures and
that's
why we see certain crimes in indian
society today
it's it's not part of indian culture at
all
to act
in such a manner against women ever
okay let's see some more questions
okay this is a question about
geopolitics how is the west an ally of
india they created pakistan as a buffer
state to counter india into central asia
kalistan propaganda operates in the west
in the media the portrait india is
negative
well i have never said that the west is
an ally of india
the west is it currently wants to use
india utilize india as
hopefully for them
as a counterweight to china
china is becoming a big threat for them
and in asia there's only one power that
can
really
counter counterbalance china which is
india
so that is why they are working with
with the common objective of of keeping
china in check
so that's the only
uh
perspective from there from where they
are working together with india apart
from that we are civilizational rivals
they have always
the west for the past
nearly
five centuries
has wanted to plunder and destroy india
plunder india
pillage india and destroy indian culture
and civilization that's been the project
it started with columbus and vasco de
gama
and it's still underway so they
are not allies of india from a cultural
or civilizational perspective this is a
short-term
thing that currently we have the same
enemy we have a common enemy and your
enemies enemy is my friend that way
that's how geopolitics works there is no
permanent ally or adversary it's all
about convenience it's all about the
short and medium term
so that's what's going on yes you are
right they created they broke india into
pieces
they created pakistan as a permanent uh
counterweight to india
it's a british project even the other so
what kale etc it's all
uh being done out of out of
the uk and canada mostly
and other western countries so yes the
west is in no way an ally of india if
you if if we think that way then we are
making a huge mistake
we have to do it alone
we have to rise on our own strength
we have to be confident
in our culture and our civilization and
we have to embrace
science and technology
to get ahead in the 21st century
history
is very important so that you know what
mistakes have been done in the past so
that you learn from other people's
mistakes
history is also important so that you
gain the confidence of knowing that we
were great in the past we succeeded in
the past
and we have the same genetics the same
blood so we can do it again
right
culture and civilization is important
because it gives you the right morality
the right values the right principles
and the right approach
and science and technology are the tools
that take you forward
whenever india was great in the past it
was number one in the world in science
technology mathematics astronomy all
these things
so we have to embrace science and
technology wholeheartedly big embrace
and that's what we'll take what will
take us forward
so good question sir
let me take another question from the
comments i had promised i would answer
this today
so this is a question by vinod madhavan
why did the plague not strike india
during the times of the bubonic plague
and the plague of justinian
all of europe and many places
surrounding asia were affected was the
indian it was the ancient ayurvedic
system
so advanced
so this is a very very interesting
question very fascinating question so
what was this plague the plague of
justinian happened in the 6th century
a.d
it was justin was a roman emperor the
eastern roman empire emperor
constantinople
at the peak of this plague epidemic this
was part of the first plague pandemic
that went on from the 6th century 80 to
the 8th century
nearly 200 or even more
years it lasted there are 15 to 20 15 to
17 18 major waves of
of this epidemic pandemic and it caused
the deaths of approximately a hundred
million people
in europe so the plague of justinian
happened in the middle of the sixth
century
at the peak of this epidemic in
constantinople about 10 000 people were
dying every day
and the origin of this plague pandemic
was to the east in china
surprise
big surprise it originated in china
now what is plague plague is a bacterial
illness
it is caused by a bacillus i think it's
a bacillus yeah
rod shaped bacterium
why pestis
and the mode of transition transmission
the vector is the flea
the flea is a small very small insect
that
that is a parasitic insect it it rides
on rats
so the rats are the first to be infected
they and then they wherever rats go the
the fleas also go and the fleas will
then bite human beings and that's how
the
the bacterium infects humans this was
the bubonic plague
it was later known as the black black
death
which was another plague pandemic in the
14th and in the 14th century which
killed about 200 million people
in europe about 50 to 60 of the entire
european population was wiped out this
is in the 14th century
so there are many episodes of plague and
they all originated in china
the vector is that is the flea which is
carried by rats so why was india spared
why did the plague never enter india and
that is a fascinating question i can
guarantee you your history teachers have
not thought about this or they even if
they thought about it they have not been
able to answer it
and nobody has raised these questions so
this is a very good question
and what's the answer
well the answer lies in the mode of
transmission the vector the vector is
the flea
it is carried by rats
so these rats
they somehow made their way into europe
through trade routes between china and
europe
in some way or the other
and then they were able to proliferate
in the european cities and across europe
and these rats carried these fleas
which are the actual vector of the
disease and that's how so many humans
died so
the answer lies in these rats and fleas
so i'm so at the time we also had trade
with china china and india were closer
than china and europe
so chinese traders did come to india but
how did how then did india not
get affected by this pandemic
i can tell you why
it's because india has a very specific
system of hygiene
and cleanliness
if you have a dirty environment
where rats can
proliferate
then you're gonna fall prey to the
pandemic european cities were hideously
dirty this is very well recorded
they did not have sewage systems
they had terrible garbage disposal
processes or no process at all
they used to throw waste on the streets
this is very well recorded by lots of
sources
europe was extremely dirty it was filthy
there was no sense of hygiene there was
no concept of hygiene
conversely in india
from the vedic times we had indians were
ridiculously ridiculously particular
about hygiene the first thing you do
when you wake up is to take a bath
ritual or bathing in a certain specified
manner you don't wear clothes twice ever
you wash them properly you dry them in
the sun
you don't dump garbage anywhere india
you used to have excellent
sewage disposal waste disposal systems
and all that before everything was
destroyed during the islamic turkic
invasions and later the european
invasions so india had
a ridiculously
rigorous emphasis on good hygiene and
good sanitation and all that
that's why rats just would not
proliferate in india
and that's why even if one or two cases
may have happened of the plague they
were not transmitted
and that's why that is the reason why
there was no plague pandemic in india
even though it ravaged across europe so
many times over the centuries and killed
i would say total
300 or more million europeans over the
centuries that's an enormous amount of
deaths
so that's why
there was no plague pandemic in india
when
much of eurasia even north africa was
affected so badly
but
during the british
occupation of india
you had multiple plague epidemics in
india
in the 20th in the early 20th century
this affected bombay which is now mumbai
thousands maybe tens of them i think
lacks of people died in mumbai in the
early 20th century because of the plague
pandemics people died in gujarat people
died across india in the plague
pandemics during the british occupation
of india why is that
because india's culture and civilization
had been destroyed india's
uh
sanitation systems had been destroyed
indian culture had
been become very weak people did not
have
the level of prosperity to be able to
carry out their practices and traditions
and all that
so india became
the british started the practice of
dumping sewage and waste into rivers
into into allowing garbage to accumulate
everywhere and that's how the conditions
became ripe during the british
occupation of india
for
rats to proliferate and that's how the
plague epidemics ravaged across india
during the british occupation of india
so that
is the answer
very good question
all right let us go back to the live
questions
all right we have a philosophical
question what does it mean to be human
well
to be human is what does it mean to be
human
uh
it means to not be a cat or a mouse or a
dog or a horse
or a fish
whatever it makes us different from
other species
it is what it means to be human so we
have certain endeavors that the other
species don't have
we have higher pursuits
we have much in common
with our
uh the with the other animals right
we need to eat we need to sleep we need
to uh do all these other physical
activities
and all that we breathe
we reproduce
and so on and so forth so this is what
we have in common with dogs cats mice
rats birds
fish
dolphins and so on
but we have certain things that set us
apart from them
we have a different kind of intellect we
have a much higher intelligence at least
that's what we believe
uh we have pursuits that make no sense
to animals like music
culture literature entertainment
so these are the things that may that
that make that differentiate us from
other animals
it is these higher pursuits
we have culture we have philosophy we
have ethics morality we have religion uh
we have civilizations and so on so forth
so these are the things that make us
different
from our closest relatives the
chimpanzees the gorillas the baboons the
bonobos
uh and so on so that in brief would i
would say is what it means to be human
uh i'm sure a philosopher would answer
it in much greater detail
all right
some more questions
shyam surely says who is india's true
ally
india is true allah is india itself
we can only seek alliances with
ourselves
we
cannot rely
on allies in geopolitics
because allies will you see it's how it
is alliances happen when there is a
convergence
of national interest
but when national interests start
diverging the alliance doesn't last look
at india and the ussr india and the ussr
were extremely strong allies during the
cold war
india was a satellite state of the ussr
now after the events of the 1990s india
and russia
are now not great allies we don't have a
very strong alliance we still have a
significant commonality of interests
and yet
the russians are now hedging their bets
they are
uh cooperating with the chinese they're
cooperating even with the pakistanis to
some extent right
of course the india
russia relationship is still reasonably
strong
there is still a great amount of
warmth etc between the leaders of the
two countries but it is no longer a
strategic alliance the way it was in the
20th century
and if you look at other nations again
if you look at the us for instance the
us isn't really
a strong ally of india it does take
actions that go against india's national
interest from time to time
and so on and so forth
so india a nation has no real
long-term true allies
you have to rely upon yourself and your
wits and your instincts and your
resources and your people
etc
to uh
to go forward in the world so there are
no true allies
shekhar says uh
what are your future plans for our
channel
they will be really revealed
soon enough
there will be there will be significant
changes
very soon
i will let you know soon
okay what else do we have
let me take some interesting questions
that have not been asked before
suspense yes
suspense
okay let me take one more question from
the
from the comments
this is by raj vardhan
my views your views on mithra kin
archives it claims that indira gandhi
was a kgb agent under the code name
vano true or false was the kgb involved
in lal bahadur shah 3's death
so what are the mithra kin archives
there was a guy a russian
kgb agent
called vasily mithrakin
who defected to the west in the 1990s i
think in 92 or something like that
and he brought with him entire suitcases
of handwritten notes
about the operations that he had
participated in
which were all
so these handwritten notes contained
lots of secrets alleged secrets
about the various operations of the kgb
which is russia's secret service the spy
service over over several decades
and much of this apparently is still
classified
and much of this reveals things about
the various activities covert activities
and operations
that the kgb undertook in various
countries
uh oh during the cold war the kgb was
the ussr's
uh secret service pi wing whatever you
want to call it right
so uh i think some uh versions or some
portions of this have been published
in the public domain i think it's
available in the form of some books one
or two volumes
some of it is available online some of
it is said to be still classified so we
don't know
uh
what that would be some of it is still
secret
and all of this is what this person
vasily mithrakin has alleged it cannot
be confirmed or denied now i have heard
that it claims
when it comes to india that apparently
the prime minister of india mrs gandhi
she received
funds
from the ussr entire suitcases full of
money cash it seems that's what is
alleged
there is no way for me to confirm or
deny this
i have i don't have access
to the actual uh
data to the actual information but this
is what it claims so this is this is the
allegation that is made in the mid
rocket archives the prime minister of
india herself
was receiving
large amounts of cash from the ussr and
she essentially allegedly according to
this these claims was an agent of the
kgb or the ussr
that's what has been claimed it's not me
who is saying it that's what the
mithrokin archives claim it also claimed
that the ussr the kg was able to publish
thousands of
news reports
in indian
media in in indian magazines and
newspapers and all that
and they were not even able to publish
even one percent of that in nato
countries so that's how deeply they were
able to control the indian media
yesterday somebody asked me about a
question about the indian media and i
said the indian media and the world
media has always been up for sale so if
this is true
then this totally corroborates
corroborates that
that the ussr had bought out india's
editors and newspaper publishers and
all of these people media
so apparently they published thousands
and thousands of news reports
planted stories in the indian media
to shape public opinion
and that public opinion you see in the
in those
those perspectives those narratives
those beliefs you see in the in in the
minds and thoughts and pronouncements of
the people who grew up in those days
very much pro ussr and very much pro
socialist pro communist and and
that entire world view right
so apparently the ussr was able to
influence india that much through by by
corrupting india's media
so these are the claims that have been
made i don't know if they are true or
false i don't have the means to verify
or or to corroborate or deny these
claims but that's just what is alleged
and that's what i can say was the kgb
involved in the in the death of lal
bahadur shastra the prime minister of
india it's it's possible
i've even heard some claims being made
that were made by
former cia agents that the cia was
involved in the death of
prime minister shastri
again
i don't have the information
this information i'm sure the indian
government would
know better than me but i'm sure it is
highly classified and it will not be
revealed anytime soon i expect
but it does look like it was not a
natural death it looks like it was
poisoned
and
maybe someday we will know the truth
as of today we don't
okay
let's take a couple more questions
uh
okay let's take this one
kanukani
if our sun explodes or dies what will be
the impact on the earth can we survive
it
well this event
so the sun will never go supernova the
sun will simply become a red dwarf
a red sorry a red supergiant
it will expel its outer layers and then
it will die slowly as a white dwarf
slowly over time it will never go
supernova it is not massive enough to go
supernova now this will happen several
billion years in the future
1 billion is 10 crore so this will
happen approximately five or so
approximately billion years in the
future
if you look at the human history
homo sapiens is about
two and a half lakh years old
the human species is about
two to four million years old is a
distinct species
distinct from our chimpanzee cousins
so four million is how long we have
lived
and this event is going to happen five
billion years in the future the age of
the earth itself is about three and a
half or so roughly roughly billion years
so this event will happen in the future
at a time span at a time scale that is
longer than the age of the earth itself
so will humans still be alive
that is
i mean it's
seriously doubtful right
we have seen species come and go on the
planet
65 million years ago you had a whole
different kind of
zoo
a different situation on the planet you
had dinosaurs that were the
dominant
family of species
today they are a minor family of species
of birds
so species come and go certain species
last several million years some species
last hundreds of millions of years if
they are lucky
but i don't know of any species that has
survived a billion plus years
so i think it would be highly unlikely
that humans would still be
here on the earth
when this event happens maybe we will
survive and go on to some other star
system because this event is coming
so uh
so it won't really affect humans
whether we survive or not
when this happens what will be the
impact of the earth so when the sun
becomes a red supergiant it will most
likely engulf the earth
and the earth will be burnt to a crisp
and later uh as these outer layers go
away earth will still survive but there
will be no life left if there was any
life
still surviving at that point so that's
uh kind of what will happen
right
okay rahul says why are we the quad not
recognizing taiwan as a country what are
we afraid of the question is what will
we gain
by recognizing taiwan as a country what
geopolitical advantage will be gain
by giving the title of country to taiwan
see the world doesn't change when you
give a new name or a new label
to a piece of land
what changes the world yesterday i spoke
about the great german german chancellor
otto von bismarck
he said that the world is not changed by
eloquent speeches
it is not changed by words
what changes the world what shapes the
future of the world
is blood and iron
what he meant was
action
so giving
a label to taiwan a new label is not
going to change the world
words don't change the world it is
actions that change the world
and again there is a consequence that
there are consequences that if the world
will face
if they
recognize taiwan as a country yesterday
i spoke about the fact that china
controls more than 95 of this global
supply of uh rare earth metals
which are
a critical component of all high
technology devices and and
defense equipment
so if you recognize taiwan as a country
they will cut off their supply the
supply to your country and then how will
you manufacture anything
so these are
costs that china can actually impose on
india and and other countries
if we recognize taiwan as a country
so the chinese have been able to achieve
the status through decades of hard work
so if we want to be in a position with
that where we can change the world we
will also have to
put in the decades of hard work of going
in the right direction
putting a label on a country you see is
not going to change the world it's not
going to do anything
change anything on the geopolitical
chess board it is actions
not words that change the world so
that's why nobody is bothering to
recognize that one as a country because
there is no real
benefit to be gained from that
right
okay let's um
let us see something interesting
shri krishna says is the chola empire
the greatest thalassocracy
thalassocracy of india
our indian history school textbooks not
showing the contributions of south india
and maharashtra to indian culture
indian history textbooks have done a
terrible job of representing the
southern part of india the eastern part
of india and
possibly maharashtra also
in in india's history right
i mean
before 2016 nobody had heard of the
cholas
has anybody heard of the of the cheras
the pandyas
has anybody heard of the
of the uh
great kaling of the great kalingas
the gangas
the other the other dynasties of kalinga
who did so much to to promote indian
culture globally
especially in eastern asia
we don't know about any of these things
because india's history textbooks have
always been north india centric
and turkic-centric mughal-centric
that's all they want to glorify that's
all they want to focus on
in the 1980s and 1990s etc there was
this tv channel called doordarshan
which showed everything from a new delhi
perspective
so india's history textbooks are also
like that everything is north india
centric
the chola empire was one of the greatest
thalassocracies of india
what is the thalassocracy it means a
maritime empire
the chola empire was one of one of the
greatest maritime empires of the entire
world
in entire in the entire human history
so yes the torahs were great
the kingdom of kalinga the empires of
kalim kalinga were also great
many of these dynasties in southern
india
have been totally marginalized the
chalukyas the sadwahanas
so many
there are so many dynasties that are not
even mentioned that nobody even knows of
so i agree that indian history textbooks
have not shown the contributions of
southern india of eastern india of
maharashtra of the great marathas come
on
of the great or homes
of the states of northeast india of the
great
dynasties in manipur for instance
nothing nothing at all nobody ever heard
of these things
so yeah this needs to change and if the
government doesn't change it we need to
change it
all right let us take
let's see how many
questions
yeah good question so this is by uh
surya
the question is if the pashtuns are much
closer to indians in terms of regional
culture and
ethics as many of them had jaat and
gujjar ancestry
why do they have surnames such as ali
khal and etc showing islamic information
well
yeah okay
so the question is why do the pashtuns
of today
have islamic names and
names that don't sound indian at all
stanix zai
and uh
ali khalil like you said
and if you i mean what examples what
other examples do we have lots of other
examples i'm sure
karzai
right and so on why do they have such
names well let me ask you different
questions
how many
what is the person what is the
percentage of muslims in india's
population
about 20 percent
india has more than 200 or 300 million
muslims
what kind of surnames do they have
many of them have i mean not many of
them 99.99 of them have indian ancestry
so what surnames do the indian muslims
have
they have arabic surnames right and
arabic first names also
so then why is why are we surprised that
the pashtuns also have such such
surnames
so they have surnames that seem to be
turkic in in in
origin
or whatever
ali
i believe that
there is a significant turkic influence
there was a significant turkic influence
i don't believe it i know for a fact
that there was a significant turkic
influence in gandhar after it was
conquered by the turks
and
the demographics and culture was changed
so that's why these this particular
system of nomenclature was introduced in
this region and that's why despite the
indian ancestry that they have which i
demonstrated yesterday from the genetic
research papers despite having in the
indian ancestry the pashtuns have these
foreign sounding
surnames and islamic first names because
of the past 1000 years of history it's a
consequence
of the past 1000 years of history
all right
we are getting to the end of today's
thing shall i take one more question
raj vadhan says is the big what is the
big bang theory is this theory
completely right the big bang theory is
the history
of the entire universe starting from the
very initial moments after
the universe was born
until today so that is the big bang
chronology
that is a physical cosmology that is the
big bang theory
so it says that the universe
was born
you could say
about 13.8
roughly billion years before today
it expanded out of a single singularity
apparently
that's what
that's the best information that we have
and there was a period of inflation
cosmic inflation and and so on and so
forth and today the universe exists in
the state that it is as a consequence of
all the events that happened after that
that is the best theory that we have as
of today is it completely right i am
sure we will make improvements to this
theory
maybe there will be some changes in the
future that is
the natural
course that you will always see in
physics
the things you as as more data is
available
the picture changes and then you make
improvements
to the theory
is the theory completely right now there
are big gaps there are big
there are many things that we don't
understand that we don't know we don't
understand
we we don't quite know what caused the
big bang
why the four forces are the way they are
uh we don't know the the nature of dark
matter dark energy
where do they come from and so forth so
there are many many many gaping holes
in the theory and yet this is the best
theory that we have as of today
so that is what i can say about this and
that brings us to the end of today's
session thank you very much for all the
questions really enjoyed
interacting with you all
and we shall keep on doing this so i
will see you again same time same
channel next week
until that time thank you so much take
care
and see you soon